Today's דף daf is
פא. peh-aleph. Start a little bit further in this context.
In the middle of, a little higher, yeah.
So we start a little bit
from פב peh-bet and we were in the middle of the discussion
of the relationship of of course לחמי תודה lachmei todah to the
תודה todah and especially what happens when you create a substitute. So
we pick up here in the middle of, where were we?
Towards the top
of פב, peh-bet, correct? And it says the following: We had just
talked about what if you created two substitutes, we got lost sequentially.
And now we're going to say a similar discussion by a חטאת.
chatas. So it's about fifteen lines down or so, line starts with
the word וכן לעניין חטאת. ve-chein le-inyan chatas. חטאות, chataot, maybe about
twenty lines down. וכן לעניין חטאות, ve-chein le-inyan chataot, the same הלכה
halacha would apply to a חטאת. chatas. הפריש חטאתו, hifrish chatato, you
separated out a חטאת, chatas, ואבדה, ve-avda, it got lost, והפריש אחרת
תחתיה, ve-hifrish acheres tachteiha, then a substitute. Now remember here the הלכה
halacha is is that if it's a substitute for חטאת, chatas, the
one you don't use is מתה. meisa. By the תודה, todah, the
one you don't use is, doesn't get bread. By a חטאת, chatas,
the one you don't use is מתה. meisa. So let's take a
look. ואבדה, ve-avda, then the second one got lost, והפריש אחרת תחתיה,
ve-hifrish acheres tachteiha, then you made a third one, ונמצא ראשונה, ve-nimtza
rishona, and now you found the original one. So now you have
one, two, and three. והרי שלוש עומדות, ve-harei shalosh omdos, and all
three of them are standing in front of you.
נתכפר בראשונה, nitkaper berishona, so again the first opinion of אביי Abaye
or it's רבא Rava rather is going to be that you look
at them in pairs. So נתכפר בראשונה, nitkaper berishona, if you use
the first one for your חטאת, chatas, so what happens?
נתכפר בראשונה, nitkaper berishona,
שנייה תמות, shniya tamus, so the second one is a substitute חטאת
chatas which didn't get used, therefore it has the הלכה halacha that
it dies. So that's because of the relationship of one and two.
If you use one, then two is the substitute חטאת chatas which
wasn't used. שלישית, shlishis, but now you look at three, so that
the three-two pair. So two was never functioned as a חטאת. chatas.
So if two was never functioned as a חטאת, chatas, so three
was never a substitute חטאת. chatas. So therefore you don't have to
let it die, תרעה, tire, you let it graze and then you
redeem it when it has a מום. mum. Similarly, נתכפר בשלישית, nitkaper
bashlishis, if you use the third one, שנייה תמות, shniya tamus, so
the three-two pair, the three is the one you used, the two
is the one you didn't, the two is a substitute חטאת, chatas,
it dies. וראשונה, ve-rishona, the first, you look at the one-two pair,
so the first one is, so two was never served as a
חטאת, chatas, so therefore one was never a substitute חטאת. chatas. So
therefore תרעה, tire, it is allowed to graze. נתכפר באמצעית, nitkaper bamtza'is,
however if you use number two, so when you look at the
one-two pair, one was the substitute חטאת chatas because two was the
real חטאת. chatas. And when you look at the two-three pair, three
was the substitute for two because two was the real חטאת. chatas.
So now both of them have that
status, שתיהן ימותו, shteihan yamusu, they
both die.
That's what רבא Rava says. אביי אמר, Abaye amar, and אביי Abaye
says אפילו נתכפר באחת מהן, afilu nitkaper be-achas me-hen,
I don't care which one of them you use, שתיהן ימותו, shteihan
yamusu, the other two die. כולו חליפין דהדדי נינהו, kulu chalifin de-hadadi
ninhu, they're not just pairs here, a one-two pair and a two-three
pair. Everything is coming to replace the first one that got lost
and they're just constant replacements of the first one. So therefore whichever
one you use, the other two are the substitutes which were not
used and they all die. The same way by the תודה, todah,
whichever ones you don't use were the substitute תודות todot and do
not get bread. So given that's obviously a very analogous debate, so
the גמרא Gemara says מאי וכן, mai ve-chein, why did you have
to give this whole second case about a חטאת? chatas? Obviously it
would be the same. No, מהו דתימא, mahu de-teima, I might have
thought התם הוא דאיכא למימר, hasam hu de-ika le-meimar,
I would have thought רבא's Rava weird idea that you go by
pairs and that if you have you know and that maybe you
you bring extra bread you do bring bread with some of the
others even the ones that weren't used, maybe that's because by a
תודה todah you always have the possibility that you're making a new
תודה. todah. Remember we had that if it wasn't an obligation and
you set aside another one then it's considered to just be a
new תודה, todah, not a substitute. So since you had that possibility,
you could understand why רבא Rava might say that the ones that
were not somehow paired up with a תודה todah in the end
are seen as new תודות. todot. And therefore he says they bring
bread. Okay? אבל הכא, aval hacha, therefore that's why רבא Rava said
that. אבל הכא, aval hacha, but by a חטאת chatas דליכא למימר
מרבה בחטאות, de-leika le-meimar marbe be-chataot, here by a חטאת chatas you
don't have the option to be מרבה בחטאות. marbe be-chataot. So everything
at most could only be a substitute חטאת chatas and therefore if
not used would have to die, so maybe he would agree to
אביי. Abaye. אימא לא, eima lo, maybe he would never have said
his position. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that nevertheless he does
say his position even if you can't be making a new חטאת,
chatas, if in the end he looks at things as pairs, and
if the thing it's paired with was not a חטאת, chatas, then
this does not have a status of a substitute חטאת chatas and
would not have to die, would just be allowed to graze till
there's a מום. mum. Okay, so that was just a wrap up
of what we were in the middle of yesterday. Now we're רבי
חייא Rebbi Chiya is going to introduce a new case. Again obviously
a variation of the theme of the משנה Mishna about things that
you don't bring bread for, but going to introduce a sort of
a complicated case where you don't have a good solution. And the
entire rest of this דף daf and the first עמוד amud of
the next דף daf to get to the משנה Mishna is going
to be trying to come up with a solution for רבי חייא's
Rabbi Chiya conundrum. So let's take a look. Okay, so תני רבי
חייא, Tani Rabbi Chiya, so רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya taught, תודה שנתערבה
בתמורתה. Toda Shenit'arvah B'tmuratah. You have a תודה Toda and you have
a תמורה, Tmura, you were irresponsible enough to try to make a
תמורה Tmura and you violated that הלכה halacha anyway, and therefore what's
the status of a תמורה? Tmura? The status is is that you
don't bring the bread. Okay, but what happens? You got the two
mixed up, sort of like Michael's case. There you see Michael, you
anticipated more or less the next case in the גמרא. Gemara. So
what a surprise. So it got mixed up with its תמורה. Tmura.
One of them brings bread, one you don't, but you don't know
which is which.
ומתה אחת מהן. Umesa achat mehen. Now, if they were both alive,
big deal, you bring both of them, you bring your loaves of
bread and you say whichever one is the תודה, Toda, these loaves
of bread are assigned to it. But now one of them died.
So now the other one you have to bring, but you don't
know if it gets bread or not. You don't know if it
was the original or תמורה. Tmura. Okay, חברתה אין לה תקנה. Chavartah
ein lah takanah. There's no solution to what's left, to the remaining
one, because you can't bring it without bread, a תודה Toda without
bread you're not יוצא, yotze, you can't bring it with bread, presumably
because as we're going to see in a minute, you know, the
real question is why can't you bring it with bread? Why can't
you just say, okay, I mean, you don't put the bread on
the מזבח, Mizbeach, you walk with your loaves into the מקדש Mikdash
and you basically say here's this animal, if it happens to be
a תודה Toda these are the bread, if not then this is
just סתם stam bread, end of story, because the problem is going
to be חולין בעזרה, Chullin Ba'azarah, okay, because if it's not a
תודה Toda then this bread isn't הקדש hekdesh and therefore it's חולין
Chullin and it's חולין בעזרה. Chullin Ba'azarah. Now this gives תוספות Tosfos
a nice opportunity, this long תוספות Tosfos here, to discuss when exactly
is it חולין בעזרה. Chullin Ba'azarah. I mean תוספות Tosfos says like,
do you mean to say I'm going to paraphrase a little, if
I walk in with my bag of potato chips into the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash it's חולין בעזרה? Chullin Ba'azarah? He doesn't say that,
but anyway, you know. So okay, how about my clothes? They're not
הקדש, hekdesh, you know, how about, you know, so תוספות Tosfos says
no, חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah is basically, although sometimes it's hard to
define the exact parameters, but it's basically when the thing is presented
as a קרבן. korban. So what makes these loaves presented as a
קרבן? korban? They're not put on the מזבח. Mizbeach. Well we're going
to find out in a minute, this is very surprising, we've never
said this explicitly yet, exactly four loaves that you give to the
כהן Kohen out of the forty get waved with the תודה, Toda,
which is interesting, we've never said that before. I mean the גמרא
Gemara did talk before about bread coming with the קרבן, korban, but
they were talking about like the עומר Omer and the שתי הלחם
Shtei Halechem where it explicitly talks about waving. Anyway, so they're waved
with the תודה. Toda. Waved with the תודה, Toda, they're being presented
as a קרבן. korban. So that would be חולין בעזרה. Chullin Ba'azarah.
תוספות Tosfos also assumes, and the גמרא Gemara actually assumes, that even
before you get to the waving, the very fact that you're bringing
them and sort of saying here's my תודה Toda frames it as
being presented as a קרבן korban even if you're not actually doing
a ritual with it. But חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah has that they're
somehow being presented as a קרבן. korban. So that is the challenge
here. If you don't know whether it needs bread or not, you
don't want to have a חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah problem.
But this is the תודה Toda now though because there's only two
of them and one died.
Yeah, but it's not חליפי תודה, chalifei Toda, if it's a חליפי
תודה chalifei Toda you'd be right, it's a תמורת תודה, tmuras Toda,
so if it was the תמורה Tmura it never gets bread, it's
only a derivative קדושה kedusha and never gets bread.
Yeah, but now it is the תודה. Toda.
No it's not, it's always the תמורה, Tmura, because it is, it
always has the קדושה kedusha that it came from having derived from
the original.
So you'd have to bring another תודה Toda then?
If you have a חיוב chiyuv to an תודה Toda like you
accepted הרי עלי arei alay and you have to bring another תודה.
Toda. But let's say for now.
But you don't know though, because this is, you don't know.
Right, that's also a problem, exactly.
So that's what I'm saying, meaning it really could be the תודה,
Toda, so why can't you just say this is now?
No it can't, if you have to bring a תודה Toda you
have to bring a new thing and designate it as a תודה.
Toda. This קדושה kedusha is always תמורת תודה. tmuras Toda.
So then no matter what you'd have to bring a new תודה.
Toda.
No, if it's the original you don't have to bring a new
תודה. Toda.
But since you don't know.
Oh so that you, if it weren't for the bread problem wouldn't
be a problem, you'd be מקדיש makdish a new קרבן korban and
say if that's the תודה Toda this is, you know, a new
תודה, Toda, or this is a שלמים Shlamim or whatever, and if
that's not the תודה, Toda, if that's the תמורה, Tmura, then this
is the תודה Toda I'm obligated. That you could solve, but the
bread is going to be... Now why don't you use that to
help with the bread? Well we'll take a look. That's what the
rest of the גמרא's Gemara discussion is going to be.
Yeah, I understand exactly, something that's presented as a קרבן, korban, doesn't
that make it הקדש hekdesh by itself?
Well, well, why was it that something that is eligible to be
a קרבן korban would be חולין בעזרה? Chullin Ba'azarah? So if you
bring in a non-sanctified animal,
right, well that's what you're doing, you're bringing in this bread, right,
so if you didn't sanctify it then it's חולין. Chullin. If you
did sanctify... So what you're going to do? You're going to sanctify
it like בתנאי bit'nai and say if I need it,
it's לחמי תודה, lachmei Toda, if I don't need it then it's
not לחמי תודה. lachmei Toda. So then if you didn't need it
you were... you had brought in חולין בעזרה. Chullin Ba'azarah.
You shouldn't bring it in then in such a case.
You mean leave it out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? Oh,
so we're going to get to that. What happens if the bread
is out of the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? But the four loaves
that you have to give to the כהן Kohen have to be
in the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Okay, so all of this is
going to be the rest of the discussion today, so let's take
a look. And what's actually interesting is it seems like, you know,
the אמוראים Amoraim really got into this like, you know, like it
was like almost like a like a fun little riddle, like how
could we figure out how to solve this problem? Okay, so that's
all רבי חייא Rabbi Chiya said. No תקנה. takanah. You and Michael,
you'll see, it'll be suggested. Okay, let's take a look. So now
the גמרא, Gemara, that's the end of רבי חייא's Rabbi Chiya statement.
Now the גמרא Gemara switches, you can see the shift to Aramaic
to analyzing it. היכי נעביד? Heichi na'avid? What should we do? נקריב
לחם בהדה, Nakriv lechem bahadah,
bring bread with it, דילמא תמורה היא, dilma tmura hi, maybe it's
only the תמורה Tmura and therefore you can't, implicitly חולין בעזרה, Chullin
Ba'azarah, that'll be said explicitly later.
לא נ... דילמא תודה היא, Dilma toda hi, maybe it's a תודה,
toda, and a תודה toda without bread you're not יוצא, yotzei, it
doesn't count as a תודה, toda, you're not יוצא yotzei your obligation.
Okay, so דילמא תודה היא. dilma toda hi. Where were we?
I just lost my line. Okay, דילמא תודה היא. dilma toda hi.
היכי דמי? Heichi dami? So now the גמרא Gemara wants to figure
out, first of all, what exactly is the case? אי דאמר עלי,
Ee de'amar alai,
if he said like I have an obligation to bring a תודה,
toda, he has a standing obligation, לא סגי דלא מייתי ליה בהמה
אחריתא. lo sagi delo maysi lei beheyma achrita.
So first of all, it's very much like what he was saying.
If he has an obligation, he can't just ignore the case. He
has to bring another animal because he has to be sure he's
satisfying his תודה toda obligation. And this might not be another תודה.
toda. So you're going to bring another animal anyway. So what are
you going to say? ולחם, Velachem, and you're going to bring bread,
ולימא, veleimar, and you'll say the following: אי הך דקיימא תמורה, Ee
hach dekaima tmura, if the one that survives is a תמורה, tmura,
הא תודה, ha toda, this new one is going to be a
תודה toda because I got to bring a תודה toda anyway, והלחמה,
ve'lachmah, the bread I'm bringing with it is its bread. אי הך
דקיימא תודה היא, Ee hach dekaima toda hi, if the one that
survives was a תודה, toda, הא לחמא, ha lachma, then the bread
goes with that one that survived,
והא, ve'ha, and how about this new animal? תהא אחריות, Tehei achrayus,
will be a backup. Okay, now, because what you're allowed to do
is you're allowed to basically say, right, this was sort of like
the חליפין, chalifin, but it's like a חליפין chalifin ahead of time.
If you remember we learned that case yesterday where at the very
outset you designate two because you're afraid things are going to get
lost, and one you've designated as the backup. So that has a
קדושה. kedusha. Now, that's much... I have a perfect solution. You bring
a second one with bread. You say if that's the תמורה, tmura,
this is the תודה toda and this is the bread. If that's
the תודה, toda, then this new animal I'm bringing is the backup
animal, and this bread goes with the first one. Then what happens?
Let's... you bring all of them. Why? Because if I מקדיש makdish
something as אחריות, achrayus, as a backup, it also gets brought. But
what's the הלכה? halacha?
אחריות Achrayus of a תודה, toda, which is like a חליפי תודה,
chalifei toda, doesn't get bread. So I've solved the problem, right? If
the first one wasn't a תודה, toda, the new one is a
תודה toda with bread. If the first one is a תודה, toda,
this is a backup which doesn't get bread, and the bread goes
with the first one. Schwartz says, I got the solution. What's the
issue?
Is there any kind of הפסק? hefsek?
Oh, of when you bring them?
The bread would go with the second one but would be...
We don't do anything with the bread. That's the funny thing. You
don't put it on the מזבח mizbe'ach or whatever.
So there isn't any kind of contiguity, no time?
Oh, you mean like physically touching or what do you mean?
Like time, isn't it brought together at the same time?
Right, yeah, so they're all there in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash
at the same time. I mean, no, the question's like do they
have to be touching? No. What you are going to see later
is you're going to have to do like you do a תנופה
tnufa with the bread and the like the breast and the thigh
of the תודה toda like a שלמים. shlamim. So that's also we
haven't sort of exactly figured that out with which breast and thigh
do you do it? Maybe you do it with both, you know,
that's never fully spelled out.
Wasn't there also
יוחנן Yochanan who
said that there was potentially a disagreement?
About what? About ולד?
vlad?
No, that was about ולד. vlad. This is אחריות. achrayus. Okay, so
let me get that centered. Anyway, okay, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara says. Let's take a look at why that's not an answer.
והא תהא אחריות. Ve'ha tehe achrayus. גמרא Gemara says, לא צריכא דאמר
הרי זו. Lo tzericha de'amar harei zo. You're right. If actually he
had a personal obligation, it would have solved the problem. But he
didn't have a personal obligation. He only said, this is a תודה
toda and this is its תמורה tmura and then one got lost.
So since he has no personal obligation, he can't work with the
structure of אחריות. achrayus. If I don't have an obligation,
I cannot sanctify something as the backup because there's no concept of
a backup. And therefore, since I can't create that idea of a
backup, I'm stuck, right? This solution said make a new one, either
say it's a תודה toda if I need a תודה. toda. If
I don't need a תודה, toda, it's a backup. But the concept
of backup only works if I have a personal obligation. If I
never said הרי עלי, harei alai, I don't have a personal obligation,
then the concept doesn't work. Now at the very end, the גמרא's
Gemara going to say, well then why not just create a personal
obligation? Why not just say, okay, now I'm taking a new obligation
to bring a תודה toda and then sort of solve it that
way? The גמרא's Gemara not going to like that. But it basically
says that, you're right, if you have a personal obligation, you've got
the perfect solution: either it's a תודה toda with bread or the
other thing is a תודה, toda, this is a backup, and then
only one of them needs bread. Okay, so now the גמרא's Gemara
going to try for a couple of answers.
Yeah, but then you don't know though. Then what do you do
with...
So who cares if you know?
Oh, you mean...
says question: which one do you wave with the תודה? toda? With...
Okay, גמרא Gemara doesn't spell that out. You're right. It's interesting. You'd
probably have to do both. Or maybe you'd put all four, you
know, everything together in one big pile or something. Now it's interesting
that that's also that's not a חולין בעזרה chullin ba'azarah because everything
is הקדש, hekdesh, but you are doing some תנופה tnufa ritual with
something which doesn't require it. But somehow that's less of a problem
because it's not חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. Okay, so now the גמרא's
Gemara going to say, give a couple... a series of answers. אמרו
למדים לפני רבי. Amru lemadim lifnei rebbi. So this... this תנא tana
called למדים. Lemadim. רש"י Rashi says it's לוי, Levi, but we'll see
לוי Levi comes up later. So somebody called למדים Lemadim or maybe
it just means a learner said in front of
רבי. Rebbi.
This says אמרו, amru, so it must be a couple of people,
the students, right?
Yeah, but you sometimes have like אחרים אומרים acherim omrim and we
say אחרים acherim means one person. But right. Now what's also interesting
is that this is going back to the ברייתא braisa language, right?
Because this is... at least they said לפני רבי lifnei Rebbe and
obviously it's רבי. Rebbe. רבי חייא Rebbe Chiya was רבי's Rebbe who
was it? Nephew? Brother-in-law? I keep on forgetting. Anyway, he was the
one that said it didn't have a solution, but apparently he put
this problem out and then at that period everybody's trying to come
up with a solution. So anyway, so they said in front of
רבי: Rebbe: ולייתי לחם ולימא, V'leisei lechem v'leima, why not bring bread?
Again, it's very strange here because of the interspersing of Aramaic and
Hebrew, which is really what was really originally part of this ברייתא
Baraita and not. Anyway, why not bring bread and say the following:
אי הך דקיימא תודה תודה היא והא לחמה, Ei hach d'kayma todah
todah hi v'ha lachmah, if the one that survived goes as a
תודה, todah, תודה היא והא לחמה, todah hi v'ha lachmah, here's the
bread. ואי לא, V'ei lo, and if the one wasn't a תודה,
todah, ליפקו לחולין, lifku l'chullin, so let the bread be חולין, chullin,
meaning the גמרא Gemara it's questioning what do you mean, why not,
so what, bring the bread. If you need the bread, it's the
bread. If you don't need the bread, it's just some bread. So
meaning here it's going to spell out what the problem was. אמר
להו, Amar lehu, so he said back to them: וכי מכניסים חולין
לעזרה? V'chi machnisin chullin l'azarah? How are you allowed to bring חולין
chullin לעזרה? l'azarah? So here is the idea that you can't just
סתם stam bring the bread and say if it works it works,
if it's not it's not part of the קרבן, korban, because then
it would be חולין. chullin. And again חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah in
the sense that it's being presented as part of the קרבן. korban.
Okay, so that won't work. ולייתי בהמה ולחם, V'leisei beheimah v'lechem, so
now let's try this. Bring a בהמה beheimah with bread ולימא v'leima
and say the following: אי הך דקיימא תמורה היא, Ei hach d'kayma
temurah hi, if the one that survived is a תמורה, temurah, הרי
זו
תודה והא לחמה, harei zu todah v'ha lachmah, the new thing I'm
bringing is the תודה todah and the bread. ואי הך
דקיימא תודה היא,
V'ei hach
d'kayma todah hi, if the one that survived was a תודה, todah,
הא לחמה, ha lachmah, the bread is the bread of the
תודה, todah, והא תהא שלמים, v'ha tehei shelamim, and let this be
a שלמים. shelamim. That's a good solution. So let this second animal
be a תודה todah if it needs to be with the bread,
and if it doesn't need to be a תודה todah and the
bread goes with the other, let it be a שלמים. shelamim. So
either way the bread is קדוש, kadosh, the animal is קדוש, kadosh,
I eat all of it, שלמי ישראל. shalmei Yisrael.
Yeah, but then you're bringing שלמים shelamim with the bread at the
same time,
and then שלמים shelamim doesn't have bread. But the bread is... but
the bread is... you're bringing שלמים shelamim and the bread and the
תמורה. temurah. You're bringing all three, two animals and the bread, and
the bread goes with one of them. So the only problem is
that, like I said, it's... the גמרא Gemara doesn't really never articulates
it as a problem because it's not חולין בעזרה, chullin b'azarah, but
what we would say is the problem is, but you're like associating
bread with something it shouldn't be associated with. Like you're doing a...
or you're doing let's say the תנופה tenufah with also the meat
of the שלמים shelamim or the meat of the תמורה. temurah. You're
not doing, you're doing a ritual with something that shouldn't be done
to.
But the גמרא Gemara
doesn't somehow doesn't have that as a problem.
I mean, the person would think that maybe שלמים shelamim needs bread
or something, depends on...
Oh, you're going about a מראית עין marit ayin type of an
issue of... That's also a good question. All right, let's see how
the גמרא Gemara responds.
Is it אסור assur חולין בעזרה? chullin b'azarah?
So that's a very good question. The גמרא Gemara sort of learns
it out from the prohibition of like the reverse of שחוטי חוץ.
shechutei chutz.
I think the phrase the גמרא Gemara uses is: מה שלי בשלך
אסור אף שלך בשלי אסור, Mah sheli b'shelcha assur af shelcha b'sheli
assur, or something like that. Yeah, it's not explicit, right. And there
is a question whether it's דאורייתא d'Oraita or דרבנן d'Rabbanan about חולין
בעזרה. chullin b'azarah. So but it does become... it is a big
concern for the גמרא Gemara in a lot of places.
So did you bring your potato chips since...?
What? תוספות? Tosafot? No, that was my paraphrase of תוספות. Tosafot.
Oh, was it you?
Yeah, תוספות Tosafot says as long as you're not presenting it as...
as קרבן korban and then he tries to figure out what are
the parameters that we say you're being presented as a קרבן. korban.
Okay, so he worked through a lot of...
So no problem like having a snack while you're perform...?
Well, there might be כבוד kavod issues. I was giving it as
a חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah issue. Okay. All right. So then let's
take a look what the גמרא Gemara says. So why not bring
a שלמים? shelamim?
אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said back to them: משום דקא
ממעטת באכילה דשלמים, mishum d'ka memayet b'achilah d'shelamim, because since you won't
know if it's a שלמים shelamim or a תודה... todah... a תודה
todah is eaten only for one day, a שלמים shelamim is eaten
for two days. So you're going to have to treat it as
a possible תודה todah and you're going to have to eat it
for one day. So you are limiting the eating of the קרבן
korban and raising the potential that you will create נותר, notar, and
we don't bring... it's the phrase is אין מביאין קדשים לבית הפסול.
ein mevi'in kodashim l'veit hapesul. You don't bring a קרבן korban in
a context where you will have less than the full amount of
time to eat it. Okay. So אמר לוי לרבי, Amar Levi l'Rebbe,
so now לוי Levi said the following to רבי: Rebbe: ולייתי בהמה
ולחם, V'leisei beheimah v'lechem, here's my solution: bring a בהמה beheimah with
bread ולימא, v'leima, and say the following: אי הך דקיימא תמורה היא,
Ei hach d'kayma temurah hi, if the one that survived is a
תמורה, temurah, הרי זו תודה והא לחמה, harei zu todah v'ha lachmah,
this now new one is a תודה todah with its bread. ואי
הך דקיימא תודה היא, V'ei hach d'kayma todah hi, if the one
that survived was a תודה, todah, הא לחמה, ha lachmah, the bread
goes with that,
והא תהא מותר דתודה, v'ha tehei motar d'todah, is the leftover of
the תודה. todah. Right? Remember what our משנה mishnah said? Our משנה
mishnah said that if you basically have something that is leftover from
a תודה, todah, like a ולד vlad of a תודה todah or
so on, then it doesn't... it doesn't come with bread.
It can't be leftover afterwards.
Well, that's the question. What do you mean leftover? The leftover examples
were that number one it was sort of as a substitute, but
of course here remember it's a substitute where it's הרי עלי harei
alai and this is coming to substitute for your obligation. If it
was this case was הרי זו, harei zu, that's exactly why we
have a problem here, because if you try to do a new
one it'll be considered a brand-new one and demand its own bread.
The other example was a ולד. vlad. So you had a ולד,
vlad, you had a... you had a sort of a substitute where
you really needed a substitute, you didn't have a case of just
saying I'm מקדיש makdish it with הקדושה hakedushah of מותר תודה. motar
todah. Right? That's not a... so that's basically what רבי's Rebbe answer
is. And you've got to love this line. אמר ליה, Amar lei,
he said back to him: כמדומה אני שאין לו מוח בקדקדו. K’midumeh
ani she-ein lo moach b’kadkado. Whoa, pretty sharp! It seems to me
that he doesn't have a brain in his skull. It seems to
me you don't have a brain in your head! So וכי, v'chi,
what type of crazy suggestion is that? וכי... v'chi...
well notice that even though, when even though he was being sharp,
you would soften it a little. He said, "it appears to me",
he doesn't say that "you", he says that "he", so it appears
to me that anybody that would say such a crazy thing doesn't
have a brain in his... what?
He said it to people in front of him, it doesn't work.
Well, that's true,
okay. Anyway, וכי מפרישין תחילה למוותרות? v'chi mafrishin techilah l'mosarot? Can you
designate something to be a leftover? Leftover is a result, you can't
sanctify something with a קדושה kedusha of נותר תודה. notar toda. And
again, if the idea was just to designate it as a type
of אחריות, achrayut, אחריות achrayut doesn't work if it's הרי זו, harei
zo, if it's not הרי עלי, harei alai, not a personal obligation.
הרי זו כנגד התנאי
שלו.
harei zo k'neged
hat'nai shelo.
There you go. So יתיב רב יצחק בר שמואל בר מרתא קמיה
דרב נחמן. yasiv Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta kamia d'Rav Nachman.
So that was the end of the discussions with Rebbe, and maybe
particularly after that response nobody wanted to raise any other suggestion. So
now the discussion shifts to the period of the אמוראים. Amoraim. So
Rav Yitzchak bar Shmuel bar Marta was sitting in front of Rav
Nachman. יתיב וקאמר. yasiv v'ka'amar.
Is Marta a male name or a female name?
I'm not sure. And he was sitting and he was saying, "Wait,
how about this idea? ולייתי בהמה ולחם, v'leiti behema v'lechem, bring a
בהמה behema with bread ולימא, v'leima, say the following: אי הך דקיימא
תמורה היא, ei hach d'kayama tmura hi, if the one that survived
is a תמורה, tmura, so that's always the easy case, הא תודה
ולחמה, ha toda u'lachma, the new animal and this is the תודה
toda with its bread. ואי הך דקיימא תודה היא, v'ei hach d'kayama
toda hi, if the one that survived is a תודה, toda, הלחם
הזה יהא לתודה, halachem hazeh yehei l'toda, this is the bread that
goes to the
תודה, toda, והא תהא תמורה, v'ha tehei tmura, and let this one
be a תמורה tmura of that original תודה. toda. And a תמורת
תודה tmurat toda doesn't get bread. Now that was gotta be a
worse suggestion than Levi's, because as he says back, אמר ליה, amar
lei, he said back to him, Rav Nachman said back to him,
עני מרי, ani mari, answer me my master, ארבעים בכתפיה וכשר? arba'im
b'katfeih v'chasher? Forty on his back and you think it's okay to
do this? Meaning forty lashes. It's prohibited to make a תמורה. tmura.
לא יחליפנו ולא ימיר אותו. lo yachalifenu v'lo yamir oto. So your
solution is having him be עובר over on a לאו lav and
make a תמורה, tmura, because then you'll have something that has קדושה
kedusha of a תודה toda without bread? Your solution is having get
lashes? So by the way, it's a nice little juxtaposition, I mean
here was a really absurd suggestion to do a לאו, lav, and
he at least responded you know in a more... politely, 'Explain this
to me, what exactly are you thinking here?' rather than 'What type
of a crazy idea was that?' All right, so that's not gonna
work to make it into a תמורה. tmura. So רב אילא... Rav
Ila... now we're not done, obviously this was something that really you
know got under people's skin. So רב אילא חלש, Rav Ila chalash,
so Rav Ila got sick. על לגביה אביי ורבנן, al l'gaveih Abaye
v'rabanan, so Abaye and some of the רבנן, rabanan, רבנן rabanan here
often like means the rabbinical students, went to visit him to pay...
you know, ביקור חולים bikur cholim call. יתיב וקאמרי, yasiv v'ka'amrei, and
they were sitting, what of course do you do when you pay
a ביקור חולים bikur cholim call? You talk in תורה. Torah. So
they were sitting and saying, אם איתא לדרבי יוחנן, im ita l'de'Rabbi
Yochanan, one minute, if we פסקן pasken like Rabbi Yochanan דאמר חוץ
לחומת העזרה קדוש, d'amar chutz l'chomat ha'azarah kadosh, I think this was
your suggestion, Dov, right? Remember there was the debate before, this is
a great little גמרא Gemara because it pulls in earlier discussions, sort
of wraps things up. So remember there was a discussion when you
שחט shacht the תודה, toda, the bread becomes קדוש. kadosh. Where does
the bread have to be? Because since the bread has the status
of the קדושה kedusha of like קדשי קדשים, kodshei kodashim, it could
be eaten in all of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Could be the bread doesn't
have to be in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Could be the
bread could be anywhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. That was Rabbi Yochanan's opinion.
ריש לקיש Reish Lakish says no, to come with the תודה toda
it has to be in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash. Rabbi Yochanan
said it could be anywhere in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So it won't be
חולין בעזרה. chullin b'azarah. Have the bread right outside the בית המקדש.
Beis HaMikdash. Perfect solution! No חולין בעזרה. chullin b'azarah. So let's take
a look. אם איתא לדרבי יוחנן, im ita l'de'Rabbi Yochanan, if we
rule like Rabbi Yochanan דאמר חוץ לחומת העזרה קדוש, d'amar chutz l'chomat
ha'azarah kadosh, that the bread could be outside of the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash and be קדוש, kadosh, so לייתי לחם, leiti lacham, forget
the other animal, bring bread ולוותביה חוץ לחומת העזרה, v'liotiveih chutz l'chomat
ha'azarah, put it right outside the עזרה, azarah, put it in the
עזרת נשים ezrat nashim or something, ולימא, v'leima, say the following: אי
הך דקיימא תודה היא, ei hach d'kayama toda hi,
if the animal that survived is a תודה, toda, הא לחמה, ha
lachma, that's its bread. It just happens to be sitting out of
the בית המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, but that's okay according to Rabbi Yochanan.
ואי לאו, v'ei lav,
and if it isn't a תודה, toda, it's a תמורה tmura or
whatever, so לא ליחול עליה קדושה, lo lichol aleih kedusha, let that
bread... let the קדושה kedusha not have been חל chal on that
bread. You make a stipulation on your קדושה kedusha and it won't
be sanctified bread. And fine! And then you go ahead and you
eat the bread with you know, you eat the bread with the
קדושה kedusha of a תודה. toda. You eat the bread within a
day, but it's not חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah because it's sitting outside
of the עזרה. azarah.
Wait, what do you do with the four things that...
Ah, that's gonna be the question. What about the four that goes
to the כהן? Kohen? Right, okay, we're gonna get to that, but
right now we've solved it without חולין בעזרה chullin b'azarah because the
bread is outside. If it's קדוש, kadosh, it's קדוש, kadosh, no problem.
If it's not קדוש, kadosh, then you know, if you didn't need
it, it wasn't קדוש, kadosh, but then you eat the bread you
know in the more you know, being מחמיר, machmir, assuming the worst
case or whatever, assuming it became קדוש kadosh and you eat the
bread within a day. So but you solved the חולין בעזרה chullin
b'azarah problem. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says exactly like Michael said,
משום דאיכא ארבעה להניף, mishum d'ika arba'ah l'hanif, because there are the
four loaves you have to give the כהן Kohen that you have
to do תנופה tnufa with. Now again what's fascinating is we've never
said until this moment that you have to do תנופה tnufa with
the breads of the תודה. toda. The תורה Torah says that you
give it... truma, you know, you should take one, והרים ממנו אחד
מכל קרבן תרומה לה' לכהן הזרק דם השלמים לו יהיה, V'hirim mimenu
echad mikol korban trumah l'Hashem lakohain hazorek dam hashlamim lo yihiye, okay
but we never say that you do תנופה. Tenufa. But because of
the other principles that when bread comes with a קרבן Korban you
do the תנופה Tenufa of the bread together with the animal, and
so the assumption here is that you do it as well. So
you take the thigh and the and the shoulder, which is what
you give from every שלמים Shlamim including a תודה, Todah, you put
the bread on it and you do the תנופה. Tenufa. So since
you have to do the תנופה, Tenufa, those four are still going
to be a חולין בעזרה Chulin ba'azarah problem.
So one would say that the same thing applies, you can't restrict
קדשים Kodshim to less than their allotted time. Right. Why wouldn't you
say the same thing applies to חולין? Chulin?
Because by חולין Chulin it's only like a wasting food problem, which
does not bother the גמרא Gemara the same way the גמרא Gemara
had a problem like letting animals die. Right, wasting חולין Chulin is
not a problem for the גמרא, Gemara, wasting קדשים Kodshim is. That's
basically what it boils down to. We can put that in the
category of things we have problems with together with the letting the
חטאת Chatat die. But yes, that is the assumption. Okay, so anyway
the גמרא Gemara says like this: משום דאיכא ארבעה להניף, Mishum d'ika
arba l'hanif, היכי לעביד? Heichi l'avid? What are you going to do?
לינפינהו אבראי, Linfinhu avrai, do תנופה Tenufa outside the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, which is where you're keeping this bread? לפני ה' כתיב, Lifnei
Hashem ksiv, whenever it says תנופה, Tenufa, it says you do תנופה
Tenufa before God, and this would not be excluded. So
לגוואי, L'gavai, bring it into the בית המקדש? Beis Hamikdash? קא מייתי
חולין לעזרה, Ka mayti chulin l'azarah, you're back to חולין בעזרה. Chulin
ba'azarah. And here you really see why it's a more significant חולין
בעזרה Chulin ba'azarah problem, particularly by these loaves, because you're waving them
and you're involving them in this whole ritual. הלכך לא אפשר, Hilkach
lo efshar, therefore you can't solve it with the bread. Okay, so
מתקיף לה רב ששת בריה דרב אידי, Maskif lah Rav Saisa brei
d'Rav Idi, so רב ששת בריה דרב אידי Rav Saisa brei d'Rav
Idi asked: אם איתא לדרב חזקיה, Im isa l'derab Chizkiya, ah one
minute, let's go back to another discussion we had earlier in this
פרק. Perek. חזקיה, Chizkiya, דאמר, d'amar, what does חזקיה Chizkiya say? קדשו
ארבעים מתוך שמונים. Kidshu arbaim mitoch shmonim. Remember there was a question
if you can bring eighty loaves and say forty of them will
be קדוש. Kadosh. Now of course תוספות Tosafot points out it's not
only חזקיה, Chizkiya, the real debate in the גמרא Gemara earlier was
if you weren't clear what you were trying to do. You had
eighty loaves, were you trying to say forty out of eighty, or
you're trying to say all eighty? But everybody agrees if you're explicitly
saying forty out of eighty, you can do it. So now what
you're going to basically do is you're going to bring eighty and
you're going to basically say: if I need forty, forty will be
קדוש, Kadosh, if I need eighty, all eighty will be קדוש. Kadosh.
So let's see what you're going to do. Okay, so ליתי בהמה,
Leisi behema, bring a new בהמה. Behema. וליתי שמונים בהדה, V'leisi shmonim
bahadah, now you got your eighty loaves of bread. ולימא, V'lima, and
say the following: אי הך דקיימא תודה היא, Ei hach d'kayma Todah
hi, if the one that survived is the תודה, Todah, הא נמי
תהוי תודה, Ha nami tehvei Todah, let this be a תודה. Todah.
והא שמונים דתרוייהו, V'hashmonim d'travaihu, and now I've got eighty loaves of
bread, right, forty and forty, it's perfect. אי הך דקיימא תמורה היא,
Ei hach d'kayma tmurah hi, if the one that survived was a
תמורה, Tmurah, הא תודה, Ha Todah, this is the תודה. Todah. והא
לחמה, V'ha lachma, and this is it and this is its bread,
I got eighty loaves.
וליקדשו ארבעים מתוך שמונים, V'likdishu arbaim mitoch shmonim, and only forty of
them are קדוש Kadosh and the other forty are אחריות, Achrayus, are
backups. Now why is it okay? You're still bringing forty חולין Chulin
loaves into the עזרה. Azarah. Because you're allowed to bring sort of
things that are needed for the קרבן Korban into the עזרה. Azarah.
That's not considered חולין בעזרה. Chulin ba'azarah. For example רש"י Rashi and
תוספות Tosafot both quote the famous story about הלל, Hillel, right, it
speaks about how הלל Hillel wanted to be very careful never to
have to never like you know to misuse a קרבן, Korban, so
he would take his little sheep with him into the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash and only when he was there in the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash would he be מקדיש Makdish it. So the question is
okay, but until you were מקדיש Makdish it, it was חולין בעזרה.
Chulin ba'azarah. So he says no, it's not חולין בעזרה, Chulin ba'azarah,
I'm doing it as part of the way in which I'm bringing
my קרבן, Korban, it's like a צריכי קרבן. Tzrichei korban. So they
say the same thing would be here too: if you have eighty
but forty are serving as the backup for the original forty, then
they're not considered חולין בעזרה, Chulin ba'azarah, they're there to serve a
purpose. What then?
You
take you have eighty loaves, you take four loaves out of them
and you give them to the כהן. Kohen. Now the question is
exactly how you define which are the loaves and how do you
you know know which to give the כהן. Kohen. Like maybe you'd
have to give forty-four, so you know you're getting at least four
from, you know what I mean, from from that there can't be
anything left over that's not. But you give what you need to
give to the כהן. Kohen. For now let's assume you can give
four and decide that those are you know the four that are
required. And then the כהן Kohen does no, I'm sorry, that would
be if you only needed forty, but because you might need eighty
because you might have two תודות Todot here, you give eight loaves
to the כהן. Kohen. Okay. Now again that's bizarre as well because,
and this is not really being spelled out, that might be the
answer, we'll see in a minute there's a question about the גרסא
Girsa of the answer, right, but now what do you give the
כהן? Kohen? So we understand why you're allowed to bring all eighty
in because even if I only need forty the other forty are
backup. But what do I give the כהן? Kohen? If I have
two תודות Todot here then I need to give, right, eight loaves
to the כהן, Kohen, four and four. So I mean or if
you want to think about it this way, the new animal is
definitely a תודה, Todah, with the new animal I give four loaves.
The old animal, which is the one we had the question, I'm
going to take four loaves and give it to the כהן Kohen
in case that's a תודה. Todah. Isn't that חולין בעזרה? Chulin ba'azarah?
If it wasn't a תודה Todah and I'm doing a whole little
ritual here with those loaves and those loaves aren't even קדוש Kadosh
or whatever, that would seem to be a חולין בעזרה Chulin ba'azarah
problem. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara responds. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says
משום דקא Mishum d'ka limit the eating of the forty. Now the
question is, is the גרסא Girsah the forty or if you look
at the side some have the גרסא Girsah is דארבעה d'arba'ah of
the four. Okay, which means the four loaves that we gave to
the כהן, Kohen, maybe those extra loaves didn't need to go to
the כהן, Kohen, and you're limiting their eating. Why are you limiting
their eating? Because there wouldn't be... no, they would've been... well again,
we're not normally concerned about limiting the eating of חולין, Chullin, but
then if they were mine and then I would've taken them home
and I could give them to basically anybody I wanted to, but
the כהנים Kohanim generally eat them amongst the family of כהנים, Kohanim,
and therefore maybe the כהנים Kohanim have so much to eat or
whatever, these won't get eaten. So by taking them out of the
potential to be eaten by ישראל Yisrael and limiting them to be
eaten by כהנים, Kohanim, so now then that is a problem. Now
again, it's a little strange. First of all, we've never really found
it before. We have found a problem of limiting the time it
can be eaten, not the fact that, oh, you can only eat
it amongst כהנים Kohanim rather than ישראל. Yisrael. Because also how hard
is it, you know, to eat four loaves? I mean 40 loaves
maybe, but four loaves, even though these were big loaves as we've
seen before. But the other thing that really bothers me much more
than that is not the issue about, you know, is not that
answer, but exactly the question that we just raised, which is: how
can you take, you know, four loaves and do the whole ritual
and not call it חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah just because it might
be true that they might be קדשים Kodshim in the sense that
these are the לחמי תודה Lachmei Todah or backups of לחמי תודה?
Lachmei Todah? But again, it's a little bizarre to take these things
and do this whole תנופה Tenufah with them and that's not a
חולין בעזרה Chullin Ba'azarah problem. It just shows you... look, it was
sort of implicit before as well. For some reason, the גמרא Gemara
is not so bothered if you do these unnecessary rituals as long
as they're all קדשים. Kodshim. But if they were חולין, Chullin, then
somehow it gets, you know, really bothered by it.
Anyway, it doesn't like that answer, but to us it would seem
that there are other problems there as well. Okay, so now the
גמרא, Gemara, we're almost done. Okay. אמר ליה רב אשי לרב כהנא.
Amar lei Rav Ashi l'Rav Kahana. So now Rav Ashi said to
Rav Kahana, 'Here's my solution. ואי איתא לרבי יוחנן דאמר הפריש חטאת
מעוברת וילדה רצה בה מתכפר רצה בולדה מתכפר'. V'i ita l'Rabbi Yochanan
d'amar hifrish chatas me'uberet veyalda ratza bah mitkaper ratza bivladah mitkaper. So
he said like this:
he said this is like an idea of אחריות, achrayut, but remember
we can't use the אחריות achrayut idea because you don't have a
personal obligation. But Rabbi Yochanan says the following. Rabbi Yochanan says, let's
say I designate an animal for my חטאת, Chatas, it happened to
be pregnant. (And the תוספות Tosafot says this is only true
if
I sanctify it once it's pregnant. Okay?) And then it gives birth.
So because it was sanctified... this is the way תוספות Tosafot explains...
sanctified when it was pregnant, that קדושה Kedushah can equally apply to
the child as well, and that child can actually be considered the
original חטאת Chatas and can be used. Okay, so it's very similar
to the idea of if I created a substitute, but here I
didn't create a substitute, it just sort of happened by itself. But
because it was born, I can now use this ולד. Vlad. So
now we're going to say, 'Ah, so here...' (remember the whole case
was that your תודה Todah was הרי זו, harei zu, not הרי
עלי, harei alai, the concept of a substitute wasn't relevant). But you
don't need a substitute here. Here you have a natural thing that
also has the קדושה Kedushah of the mother, the ולד. Vlad. And
which, if you can use it for a חטאת, Chatas, then you
can certainly... if you had an analogous case by a תודה, Todah,
would bring the bread together with the ולד. Vlad. So let's see
how this is going to solve the problem. Okay. ואי איתא לרבי
יוחנן V'i ita l'Rabbi Yochanan דאמר הפריש חטאת מעוברת וילדה רצה בה
מתכפר רצה בולדה מתכפר. d'amar hifrish chatas me'uberet veyalda ratza bah mitkaper
ratza bivladah mitkaper If somebody separated off a pregnant חטאת Chatas וילדה
veyalda and it gave birth, רצה בה מתכפר רצה בולדה מתכפר. ratza
bah mitkaper ratza bivladah mitkaper. You can choose which one is your
חטאת. Chatas. They have equal קדושה. Kedushah. So according to that, let's
do something analogous by a תודה. Todah. לייתי בהמה מעוברת, Leisay behemah
me'uberet, get a pregnant בהמה, behemah, ולימתין לה עד שתלד. v'lamtin lah
ad sheteled. Okay, and obviously you sanctify it. Okay, you just wait
for it to give birth. Why do you need a pregnant one
to start with? Anyway, so you sanctify it, then it gave birth.
Okay,
עד שתלד, ad sheteled, ולייתי שמונים בהדה v'leisay shemonim bahadah and take
eighty loaves of bread, ולימא. v'leima. Now you have your two new
animals plus the one that you don't know what its status was,
right? Plus this new one you sanctified and now it gave birth.
ולימא v'leima and say the following: אי הך דקיימא תמורה היא, i
hach d'kayma tmura hi, if the one that survived was a תמורה,
tmurah, הא וולדה תודה היא, ha uvladah todah hi, this and its
ולד vlad are both תודות. Todot. והשמונים לתרתייהו v'hashemonim l'tarveihu and these
eighty go for both of them. ואי הך דקיימא תודה היא, v'i
hach d'kayma todah hi, and if the one that survived was a
תודה, Todah, הא נמי תודה היא, ha nami todah hi, so this
is also a תודה, Todah, והשמונים לתרתייהו הווי, v'hashemonim l'tarveihu havyu, and
these eighty... meaning the mother is a תודה Todah and these eighty
loaves go for the original one and for the mother.
והאי להוי מותר תודה, v'hai leihavei motar todah, and the child will
be the leftover of a תודה. Todah. So meaning, this really is
similar to the previous answer where the guy was told אייתי לאו
מחתכא דקדשא, ayti lav mechtacha d'kadsha, except there he tried to do
it originally, he tried to say 'I'm מקדיש makdish this as מותר
תודה'. motar Todah You can't be מקדיש makdish something as מותר תודה.
motar Todah. So here we're saying you can find, but you can
create מותר תודה. motar Todah. You sanctify an animal as a תודה,
Todah, it gives birth, what comes out is מותר תודה. motar Todah.
But if what came out was מותר תודה, motar Todah, it wouldn't
solve the problem because you wouldn't have the possibility of both requiring.
That's why we introduced the idea of רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. The
normal הלכה Halachah is that מותר תודה motar Todah doesn't get bread.
But רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says that if you want, you can...
take the child and treat it as the full קדושה kedusha of
the mother. רצה בה מתכפר רצה בו Ratza bah mitkapeir ratza bo
and so on. So therefore what you can say is, this isn't
really clear that רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan would agree to this, but
what he's saying is, if you sanctify the mother as a תודה
Toda and it came out a child, it's sort of like you
have a choice. You can call the child a full תודה Toda
and bring bread, or you can call only the mother the full
תודה Toda and the child as the מותר תודה Motar Toda and
you would not bring bread with the child. So if you have
the choice now, it's perfect. You've got three animals. You say if
the first one isn't a תודה, Toda, I'm calling the child a
תודה Toda as well, and I have two תודות Todahs with eighty
loaves. If the first one is the תודה, Toda, then I'm saying
that only the mother was the
תודה, Toda, the
eighty loaves go to
those two, and the child
is a מותר תודה, Motar Toda, which does not bring bread. What
about אותו ואת בנו? Oto v'es beno? Ah, what an excellent question!
Oh
my God! Who did? Aryeh? Oh my God! So you wouldn't do
it in one day I guess. But then, but wait, can you
bring the loaves of the תודה? Toda? No, but you can't bring
the loaves of the תודה, Toda,
it's not like נסכים, nesachim, you can't bring them on a different
day.
Oh my God, let me think.
No, but if you know what it is, it's אותו ואת בנו
Oto v'es beno and it's not אותו ואת בנו. Oto v'es beno.
It is, but they חז״ל Chazal right,
they switch it, it works אותו ואת בנו.
Oto v'es beno. Yeah, they switch it around. That's true. That's true.
And additionally, doesn't an animal have to be thirty days old or
something?
That's not a problem. As long as it can give birth and
you can wait, no, eight days old. As long as it gives
birth and you wait the eight days, and the mother is also
still within a year old. Why isn't it?
A תודה Toda doesn't have an upper limit, so that's not a
problem. A תודה Toda can be as old as it, just a
problem on the young side.
Right, right, it's only a חטאת Chatas that has to be a
year. Correct. So that's not a problem. No, no, רב יוחנן's Reb
Yochanan example, רב יוחנן's Reb Yochanan example about חטאת Chatas and ולד
vlad that they both have to, it has to be within a
year.
Why are you doing it?
You're not doing it on... No, you do one on one day,
one on the other. No, but how would that solve the bread
problem? Because if you bring the bread on different... Oh, that's true.
What you could do is like this. You bring the mother on
one day, and you bring the ולד vlad with the תמורה temura
on the second day. That's how it works. You bring the mother
on one day, the mother definitely gets forty loaves, and then you
bring the child with the leftover on the next day, and then
either the leftover's a תודה Toda and the child is a מותר
תודה, Motar Toda, so the leftover gets the forty, or the leftover
is the תמורה temura and the child is a full תודה. Toda.
But that's a good point, right. What you do is you bring
the mother on one day and the child and the תמורה temura
on the next day.
And nobody asked the question?
Nobody asked that question, that was a great question. Okay. So, that's
a great question. All right, so let's take a look. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. I mean, somebody might have asked it,
but okay, that's gotta be the solution. You just as Michael says,
you bring them on separate days. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. But you have to do it in a way so
that the bread is always, you know, working. The bread isn't, isn't
detached from the animal it has to be with. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. So that's assuming that by רב יוחנן's Reb
Yochanan case, you have the choice of how to use the, how
to use the ולד. vlad. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
אמר
ליה,
Amar
lei, so he said back to him, מאן לימא לן, Man leima
lan, who told you, דאמר רב יוחנן, D'amar Reb Yochanan, אם שירו
משוייר, Im shiyuro meshuyar, that רב יוחנן Reb Yochanan said that if
you left it over, it is left over, which means that basically
you have a choice of how to use it.
If you take a look like the, well let's see what the
רש״י Rashi in the כתב יד, ksav yad, let me see what
this printed רש״י Rashi here says. I'll just read, I can't find
it because this one doesn't have bold. Anyway the
רש״י Rashi here in the
כתב יד ksav yad frames this שירו משוייר shiyuro meshuyar the following:
שיכול להפריש לו ולולדו לשם שני קרבנות, Sheyachol l'hafrish lo u'l'vlad l'shem
shnei korbanos,
meaning that you can opt to make both the mother and the
child equal weight קרבנות. korbanos. Who told you that that's רב יוחנן's
Reb Yochanan logic? דילמא אם שירו אינו משוייר, Dilma im shiyuro eino
meshuyar, maybe you can't opt to sort of, you know, leave it
over as it were, to use the, the child as its own
independent קרבן. korban. והיינו טעמא דרב יוחנן, V'hainu ta'ama d'Reb Yochanan, this
is the reason of רב יוחנן, Reb Yochanan, because of what we
said at the beginning of the סוגיא, sugya, דאדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש,
D'adam mitkapeir b'shvach hekdesh, that you can be atoned with the שבח
shvach of the הקדש, hekdesh, but not... so yet it's again how
is this exactly different than the idea of אם שירו משוייר? im
shiyuro meshuyar? The basic difference is like this. אדם מתכפר בשבח הקדש
Adam mitkapeir b'shvach hekdesh basically says only one of them works. Doesn't
say which is I think the question that Aryeh was asking the
other day, doesn't say that you can both work. Right when רב
יוחנן Reb Yochanan says you use the child of a חטאת, Chatas,
right, that could just be understood as okay, the child of a
חטאת Chatas you can use it to be יוצא yotzei your obligation,
but it doesn't have a status of a new קרבן korban and
what's left over would be a מותר חטאת. Motar Chatas. Okay, so
here too, right, if the, if you can use the child perhaps
that's שבח הקדש shvach hekdesh as the תודה Toda itself, but it
would make the mother מותר תודה, Motar Toda, and that would not
solve our problem. Remember the only way we're trying to solve our
problem here... was we thought that if you could bring the mother
and the child, you could stipulate and say either they're both a
תודה toda if I need them both to be a תודה, toda,
or if not, one's a תודה toda and one's a מותר תודה.
mosar toda. So what the גמרא Gemara is saying now is who
told you that רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan says you have that choice?
Maybe what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying is that if you
have a child, it can serve the role of the mother, but
if it does, then the mother becomes a מותר תודה, mosar toda,
and they're not both equal status. All right, so that's, so that's
not going to work. So we're almost, we're drawing this to a
close, no good answer.
רבינא איקלע למהוזיא, Ravina ikla le-Mahuzia, so Ravina came to this place
Mahuzia. It's very interesting. Now we're like really at the end of
the period of the אמוראים, Amoraim, you know, Ravina's like this has
been a question that has not been solved for a few hundred
years, okay. So he's going to Mahuzia. אמרו ליה Amru lei רב
דימי בריה דרב הונא מדמהוזיא, Rav Dimi bereih de-Rav Huna mi-De-Mahuzia, so
this Rav Dimi of this place said to him, לרבינא, le-Ravina, said
to Ravina, here's a solution. ליתי בהמה, Leisei beheima, let's bring a
beheima, ולימא ve-leima and say the following: הרי עלי. Harei alai. Why
don't you, right, the whole problem was that you cannot make something
a substitute, right, because if you could have made it a substitute,
then it would have solved the problem because a substitute doesn't get
the bread. But so we said no, you said הרי זו. harei
zu. So he says good, solve it, create your, create an obligation
and then we can solve the whole problem. Say look, I take
an obligation as a תודה. toda. Now, and this will be the
תודה, toda, and this new animal. וליתי בהמה אחריתי, Ve-leisei beheima achreisei,
then take a third
animal, וליתי שמונים בדג ve-leisei shemonim be-dag and
get
your
eighty loaves, ולימא ve-leima and
say the following: אי הך דקיימא תמורה היא, Ei hach di-kayma temura
hi, if the original one was a temura, הני תרתי תודות, hani
tartei todah, these is two new todahs, והשמונים דתרווייהו, ve-ha-shemonim di-travaihu, and
these eighty loaves are for both of them. ואי הך דקיימא תודה
היא, Ve-ei hach di-kayma toda hi, if the original one left over
was a toda, והא דאמרי עלי נמי להוי תודה, ve-ha de-amri alai
nami le-havei toda, the one that I first designated out when I
said I'm taking an obligation, that is a new toda, והא, ve-ha,
and
this, והשמונים דתרווייהו, ve-ha-shemonim di-travaihu, and the eighty loaves, forty are for
the old one that survived, forty is for the new one when
I said הרי עלי. harei alai. How about this third animal? ואידך
תהוי לאחריות, Ve-idach tehei le-achrayus, that's a backup korban, okay? So basically
remember that was what the גמרא Gemara said at the very beginning.
Why's our whole thing? Just take a new one, make it a
backup, a backup doesn't get bread, and say if I need a
new one it's a new one, if not it's a backup and
the backup doesn't get bread. So now the גמרא Gemara is saying
oh, you can't do that because you never said הרי עלי. harei
alai. So the גמרא Gemara is now saying so say הרי עלי.
harei alai. Say הרי עלי, harei alai, make a new obligation, take
two new ones, one'll be a תודה, toda, the other one we'll
say: if I need a תודה, toda, the second one is a
תודה. toda. If I don't need a תודה, toda, it's a backup,
and as a backup it doesn't get bread, and therefore the bread
goes to the one that was left
over, giving you forty breads, eighty loaves and three animals.
But that's always sort of the structure of the solution. The structure
of the solution is going to be make it so that you
have x number of animals, and but only x minus one require
bread regardless of what, you know, regardless of what the case is.
And then you could always like stipulate. So here what we're saying
is is that I've got three animals. If the first one is
a תודה, toda, the second one is a תודה, toda, then the
third one is a אחריות. achrayus. If the first one isn't a
תודה, toda, then those two are תודות. todaos. Okay, so why not
just do that? Create an obligation which allows you to create אחריות,
achrayus, and in the case of an אחריות achrayus of a תודה,
toda, it doesn't get bread.
Okay, where were we? אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back
to
him, התורה אמרה, ha-Torah amrah, the Torah said, טוב אשר לא תדור
משתדור ולא תשלם, tov asher lo sidor mi-she-tidor ve-lo teshalem, better that
you should not make a vow rather than making a vow and
not paying it up. So the Torah's not thrilled when people say
הרי עלי. harei alai. ואת אמרת לקום לנדור בתחילה ve-at amrat lekum
lindor ba-techila and you're saying this guy should get up and say
הרי עלי? harei alai?
Well, he has to, he has this one before of, he
has this other korban that what's going to happen to it if
you don't solve the problem? Right, so תוספות Tosafot actually says that
sometimes we actually do use that as a loose solution: make a
new נדר, neder, etc., etc. But תוספות Tosafot says that's when there
are pressing things to solve. Like if you don't do this you
won't be able to bring your נזיר nazir and you won't be
able to bring your קרבן korban and therefore you're going to remain
a נזיר nazir for your whole life. So like when there are
real pressing things to solve, we'll let you do this. But here,
okay, so we have one animal which we can't solve, so it's
going to sort of be like what we say by a חטאת,
chatas, basically like let it die or let it get a מום
mum and we'll redeem it and we just won't solve the problem,
but not that we're going to encourage people to make vows. Which
is of course a little bit funny because you would think of
all the answers this is the best answer and like come on,
people are making vows every single day in the time of the
בית המקדש. Beis Ha-Mikdash. Normally the גמרא Gemara assumes and he made
a נדר neder this way and he made a נדר neder that
way and never sort of critiques it and all of a sudden
now, you know. But maybe they were enjoying too much the idea
of having this as like a puzzle. So anyway, all right, so
we had a whole range of very nice solutions which the גמרא
Gemara rejected. It was an opportunity to bring back the idea about
the idea of the loaves outside of the בית המקדש, Beis Ha-Mikdash,
חולין בעזרה. chullin ba-azarah. We saw interestingly that חולין בעזרה chullin ba-azarah
was more of a problem, you know, to have חולין בעזרה chullin
ba-azarah even just presented there as a קרבן, korban, less than it,
that was more of a problem. a ritual which was something that
didn't require that ritual. That didn't bother the גמרא Gemara so much.
חולין בעזרה Chulin Ba'azarah did. And again, this interesting idea at the
end about the חקירה, chakirah, the child of a חטאת chatas or
the child of a תודה. todah. Does it, you know, does it
basically mean one becomes the קרבן korban and the other is the
leftover? Or for here, we had an interesting idea: אם שיירו משודר,
im shiyuro meshudar, which was not fully explained here, but an idea
that almost the owner, you can choose to make them both full
full-status קרבנות korbanot or full-status קדושה, kedusha, but then the גמרא Gemara
questions that.
Okay, so we didn't solve it.
You got this תמורה, tmurah, you got to, you again you can't
bring it.
But you can't just throw it out,
you let it graze, get a מום, mum, and you redeem it.
Twice. You know, it's not like the worst thing in the world,
but it made for a lot of interesting discussion. Okay, now we
move on to the next משנה. mishnah. האומר הרי עלי תודה, Ha'omer
harei alai todah, somebody takes an obligation to bring a תודה. todah.
יביא היא ולחמה מן החולין. yavi hi velachmah min hachullin.
You have to bring it from non-sanctified things. Now that is in
contrast to מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. Meaning, normally a sanctified thing, like
if I sanctify my animal as let's say I don't know, an
עולה, olah, of course I can't bring it as an עולה olah
and also bring it as a תודה. todah. If I sanctify it
for בדק הבית, Bedek Habayis, of course it all belongs to the
בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, I can't bring it as a תודה. todah.
But, let's say it's מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni. Now, of course, you
know, מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni you don't have animals out of מעשר
שני, Ma'aser Sheni, but I have money of מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
Can I use that money? So what am I supposed to do
with money of מעשר שני? Ma'aser Sheni? Buy food and eat it
in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Well, isn't that exactly what a תודה todah is
going to be for me? It's going to be food that I'm
going to eat in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Let's use my מעשר שני Ma'aser
Sheni money to bring my תודה todah with. So this is the
principle that you cannot use your מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, אין מביאים
דבר מן החובה, ein mevi'im davar min hachovah,
anyway,
you can't bring up something that's an obligation ממעות מעשר שני. mema'os
Ma'aser Sheni. You can only bring it if it's not a personal
obligation that I'm satisfying. This by the way becomes a very important
principle for certain פוסקים poskim in terms of questions about מעשר כספים.
Ma'aser Kesafim. Because you know the classic question with מעשר כספים Ma'aser
Kesafim is can I use my מעשר כספים Ma'aser Kesafim money, if
you give מעשר כספים, Ma'aser Kesafim, can I use it to pay
my kids' tuition? Can I use it to pay my shul membership?
If so, I'm covered. Awesome. Everybody gives מעשר כספים Ma'aser Kesafim who
sends their kids to Jewish day school. So a lot of פוסקים,
poskim, the question is how much do you pattern מעשר כספים Ma'aser
Kesafim off of real מעשר Ma'aser and how much do you pattern
off of which type of מעשר, Ma'aser, מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani, מעשר
שני, Ma'aser Sheni, etc. But anyway, a number of פוסקים poskim use
the principle that you can't bring דבר בחובה davar bechovah that's already
an obligation ממעות מעשר שני. mema'os Ma'aser Sheni. So no, if that's
already part of your obligations, you can't use your מעשר Ma'aser money
for that. So that's anyway the principle here. You cannot use your
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni money if it's an obligation.
What? No, it's not all פוסקים poskim agree with that, it's all
based on how you conceive of מעשר, Ma'aser, of מעשר כספים. Ma'aser
Kesafim. That'll be another time. Anyway, so if you take a personal
obligation, you cannot use your מעשר Ma'aser money to bring your תודה.
todah. Now let's say you said תודה עלי מן החולין ולחמה מן
המעשר. Todah alai min hachullin velachmah min hama'aser. I take an obligation
to bring a תודה todah from חולין chullin money, but I want
to be able to bring the bread from מעשר Ma'aser money. So
it doesn't matter what you said. יביא היא ולחמה מן החולין. Yavi
hi velachmah min hachullin. It's all defined by the תודה. todah. This
is like what we said yesterday, right? The עיקר ikar is the
תודה, todah, the bread comes along for the ride. So since the
תודה todah has to come from the חולין, chullin, the bread also
has to come from the חולין. chullin. Now תודה מן המעשר ולחמה
מן החולין. Todah min hama'aser velachmah min hachullin. Let's say you stipulate
and you're going to say I am going to bring a תודה
todah from מעשר. Ma'aser. Now again, it's not exactly clear from this
משנה mishnah if you say like הרי זו, harei zo, right? The
משנה mishnah started with הרי עלי. harei alai. הרי עלי Harei alai
creates a personal obligation. I can't discharge my personal obligation with מעשר
Ma'aser money. Now when I say תודה מן המעשר, todah min hama'aser,
am I saying I take an obligation to bring a תודה todah
from a מעשר Ma'aser and then it's okay because I've stipulated from
the outset that I'm going to do that, or does it actually
mean that I'm not even taking it as a personal obligation to
bring it? I'm just saying this money for מעשר Ma'aser will be
used for
a
תודה.
todah. Wait, why is it okay to bring תודה todah from מעשר?
Ma'aser?
As I said, you could understand this one of two ways. Either
that originally you from the very outset you stipulated that you're going
to satisfy your obligation that way—that would be a little strange if
the principle is you can't satisfy your obligation—it should more easily be
understood which means is that you never took a personal obligation. You
just said, "This מעשר Ma'aser money I'm going to use for a
תודה." todah. I מקדיש makdish it with קדושת—yeah, kedushas because then it's
not—there's no הלכה halachah that you can't use מעשר Ma'aser money for
a קרבן. korban. The הלכה halachah is you can't use מעשר Ma'aser
money to discharge an obligation. So I never accepted an obligation. I
never said I'm חייב chayav a תודה. todah. I just said I'm
מקדיש makdish this מעשר Ma'aser money with קדושת תודה kedushas todah and
I'm going to bring a תודה todah out of it.
So there's still personal obligation because it's still an obligation, it's an
obligation to bring this.
No, it creates a קדושה, kedusha, it doesn't create an obligation. But
right, personal obligation. You cannot use מעשר Ma'aser money to satisfy a
personal obligation. Okay. Now היא ולחמה מן המעשר Hi velachmah min hama'aser
let's say you say I'm going to bring it and its bread
from מעשר. Ma'aser. Fine, so do exactly what you said, no problem.
Of course the גמרא Gemara is going to say you don't have
to bring it from מעשר, maaser, you're allowed to bring it from
מעשר. maaser. Now,
ולא יביא velo yavi when you are going to bring from מעשר,
maaser, when we do let you bring bread from מעשר maaser money,
לא יביא מחיטי מעשר שני, lo yavi mechittei maaser sheni, don't bring
from the original מעשר שני, maaser sheni, like I actually have flour,
wheat of מעשר. maaser. No, no, that you should not use wheat
of מעשר maaser to make לחמי תודה lachmei todah out of it,
אלא ממעות מעשר שני. ela mimot maaser sheni. When you transfer, you
know, most people they wouldn't bring the original, they transfer it to
money and they bring the money to ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so the money
of מעשר שני maaser sheni you can use to buy לחמי תודה
lachmei todah when it's allowed, but not the original מעשר שני maaser
sheni and we'll see why in the גמרא. Gemara. So let's take
a look at the, let's at least begin this in the גמרא.
Gemara. Let's see what time it is. Okay, we have four minutes.
Okay, אמר רב הונא. amar Rav Huna. So רב הונא Rav Huna
says, האומר הרי עלי לחמי תודה, haomer harei alai lachmei todah, if
somebody says I'm obligating myself to bring תודה todah bread. So מביא
תודה ולחמה, mevi todah velachmah, so you can't, then if you, even
though you just took an obligation to bring the bread, that's meaningless.
You can't bring תודה todah bread by itself. So if you said
I'm going to bring תודה todah bread, so you really obligated yourself
to bring the תודה todah with its bread. מאי טעמא? mai taama?
So the גמרא Gemara asks that, what's the reason? מידעי ידעי האי
גברא דלחם בלא תודה לא איקרי. meday yadei hai gavra delachem belo
todah lo ikrei. You know that you can't bring bread of a
תודה todah without a תודה. todah.
והאי, vehai, maybe you, you're my friend, and you know, then
you're obligating yourself to bring for somebody else's. That might make a
difference if that was the context. Okay, והאי, vehai, but assuming that's
not the context, והאי תודה ולחמה קאמר, vehai todah velachmah kaamar, when
you said תודה todah bread, you really meant the תודה todah with
its bread. והאי דקאמר לחמי תודה, vehai dekaamar lachmei todah, so the
fact that you said bread of a תודה, todah, סוף מילתא נקט,
sof milta nakat, because in the end the תודה todah has to
come with bread, so you spoke about like the, you know, even
even the bread, but really you have to be talking about the
whole package or else it doesn't make sense. All right, so that's
what he says. So now let's see how the גמרא's Gemara going
to ask some questions on the משנה, Mishnah, although the answers will
seem pretty obvious. תנן, tenan, our משנה Mishnah we taught our משנה,
Mishnah, תודה מן המעשר ולחם מן החולין יביא כמה שנדר. todah min
hamaaser velachem min hachullin yavi kema shenadar. If you say I'm going
to bring תודה todah from מעשר maaser and the bread from חולין,
chullin, then you're able to do what you said. You can bring
the תודה todah from the מעשר. maaser. ואמאי, veamai, why is that
true? כיון דאמר לחם מן החולין, keivan deamar lachem min hachullin, by
the time you got up to speaking about the bread and you
said the bread from the חולין, chullin, so if the bread means
bread with the תודה, todah, so when you said the bread from
the חולין, chullin, you mean the bread and the תודה todah from
the חולין. chullin. So the גמרא Gemara says יביא היא ולחמה מן
החולין. yavi hi velachmah min hachullin. So the bread should mean both.
And of course it's a silly question. Because if you say just
bread, you mean both, but if you said first תודה todah this
and bread that, obviously when you got to bread you're just talking
about the bread. So the גמרא Gemara says שאני התם, shani hatam,
that's different. דכיון דאמר תודה מן המעשר, dekeivan deamar todah min hamaaser,
once you said the תודה todah is from the מעשר, maaser, so
when you got to the bread, נעשה כאומר, naaseh keomer, this is
what Michael wanted to say originally, הרי עלי לחם לפטור תודתו של
פלוני. harei alai lachem liftor todato shel ploni. When you got to
the bread, there was already a standing obligation to bring the תודה,
todah, you've already said תודה, todah, so the bread you just meant
the bread by itself, I'm now going to bring bread from חולין
chullin to satisfy that תודה todah obligation I already articulated. But obviously
here bread does not mean bread with the תודה, todah, it just
means the bread part. Okay. אי הכי, ei hachi, the גמרא Gemara
says, if that's true, רישא דקתני, reisha dekatni, the beginning where you
say תודה מן החולין ולחם מן המעשר, todah min hachullin velachem min
hamaaser, if you say תודה todah from חולין chullin and the bread
from מעשר, maaser, then you're stuck and it all has to be
חולין chullin because you follow the תודה. todah. יביא היא ולחמה מן
החולין, yavi hi velachmah min hachullin, you follow the תודה. todah. הכי
נמי נעשה כאומר הרי עלי תודה לפטור לחמו של פלוני? hachi nami
naaseh keomer harei alai todah liftor lachmo shel ploni? Why don't we
say the same thing? That we split your statement in half? The
bread obligation you said מעשר, maaser, that works. The תודה todah comes
from חולין chullin to go together with the bread. Meaning why there,
why you know why there do we say that the word, if
we say the word bread means just bread when you're making a
two-part statement, why don't we say the word תודה todah means just
the תודה? todah? And when you said תודה todah from the חולין,
chullin, just the תודה todah has to come from the חולין, chullin,
but the bread can still come from the מעשר maaser because you
said bread separately. So the גמרא Gemara says
הכי נמי נעשה, hachi nami naaseh, why don't we say here as
well? Let me find my place.
נעשה כאומר הרי עלי תודה לפטור לחמו של פלוני. naaseh keomer harei
alai todah liftor lachmo shel ploni. Say תודה todah means just the
תודה todah and the bread can still come from the מעשר maaser
because you said bread separately. הכי השתא, hachi hashta, what type of
a question is that? בשלמא לחם למיפטר תודה אתי, bishlama lachem lemiftar
todah ati, I understand
bread to exempt a תודה, todah, that comes, you first said the
תודה, todah, that defines itself, and then you're describing what you're going
to do, you know, what type of bread you're going to bring.
תודה למיפטר לחם מי אתי? todah lemiftar lachem mi ati? You know,
you would never make the תודה todah secondary and the bread primary.
So again, it's like, you know, very straightforward what the basically the
question and the answers are all very serious. Basically it's yes, if
you say just bread by itself it could mean bread with the
תודה. todah. If you said תודה todah this, bread that, you mean
the bread separately. But when you say תודה todah a particular way,
that locks limits you in terms of what you do by the
bread because the תודה todah is the primary and the bread is
the secondary. Okay. תא שמע, ta shema, come and here we'll just
wrap this up. האומר הרי עלי תודה בלא לחם וזבח בלא נסכים
כופין אותו מביא תודה ולחמה
זבח ונסכיה. haomer harei alai todah belo lachem vezevach belo nesachim kofin
oto mevi todah velachmah zevach unesacheiha.
So if somebody wants to stipulate like מתנה על מה שכתוב בתורה,
matneh al mah shekatuv baTorah, I'm going to bring תודה todah without
the bread or זבח zevach without the נסכים, nesachim, tough luck, your
obligation of your קרבן korban requires bread. you to bring the bread
or requires you to bring the נסכים nesachim you don't get a
choice about that. So טעמא דאמר ta'ama de-amar the reason that you
have to bring the bread is because you at least said I'm
bringing a תודה. todah. אבל לא אמר תודה aval lo amar todah
if you hadn't said the word תודה todah presumably if you had
just said I'm going to bring bread you had you know because
it's saying because you said תודה todah you have to bring the
bread. But presumably if you didn't say תודה todah you just said
bread לא lo presumably you wouldn't have to bring a תודה. todah.
So the גמרא Gemara says no הוא הדין אף על גב דלא
אמר תודה hu hadin af al gav de-lo amar todah even if
you hadn't said the word תודה todah even if you had just
said I'm going to bring bread you would have had to bring
the תודה todah with the bread. ואיידי דקבעי למתני זבח בלא נסכים
va-adei de-ka-ba-ei le-mitni zevach belo nesachim but since it says if you
say זבח zevach without נסכים nesachim that there you go have to
bring both ולא מתני ליה נסכין בלא זבח ve-lo matni lei nesachin
belo zevach it could not give an example if you said I'm
going to bring just the נסכין. nesachin. You know why? Because if
you said I'm going to bring a wine libation we wouldn't say
oh that implicitly means a קרבן korban because a wine libation can
come by itself. So therefore תני נמי תודה tani nami todah we
also say תודה. todah. Okay so maybe we will end here. So
the גמרא Gemara basically here was just clarifying that if you say
just bread you mean bread and the תודה todah had some questions
which were very curious because the answers were quite obvious but okay.
But if you say just תודה todah obviously you have to bring
the bread just bread we're saying implicitly also means the תודה todah
and you also have to bring them both. When we come tomorrow
we will start unpacking the actual the you know the central aspects
of the משנה Mishna which have to do with the issue about
using the מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni money.